okay let's work on the solution for the
drop timing quiz the final question was
when does
the add here the last instruction commit
to do that we have to figure out what
happens with the last two instructions
so can we issue the subtracting cycle
five
yes we can only one of the add subtract
reservation stations is used at that
time
in cycle five it actually will be freed
so from cycle six we actually have all
the reservation stations in ads attract
available but for sure one is available
in cycle five
and then the third one we can use it in
cycle six in fact by that time this one
is also available so if we can just
issue these instructions
the subtract here uses r2 and r5 r5
is not produced by any of the previous
instructions but r2 is so we actually
have to wait until cycle 7 before we can
proceed to execution
now
because in cycle 7 other instructions
are also beginning execution we have to
figure out can we actually run this
subtract now or do we have to wait for
the next cycle so we want to run it in
cycle 7
but remember this is a multiplication
this is a subtract so they're using
different execution units and they can
begin in the same cycle if another for
example add or subtract was beginning at
seven then we would actually have to
wait until eight but because these are
different units we can begin at seven
and we're going to try to broadcast our
result at eight nobody else is trying to
broadcast at eight so we will succeed at
that
and finally
for the add here it's waiting for r4 and
r3
r4 is produced by this subtract r3 is
produced here so we need to wait for
cycles five and eight and then begin in
cycle nine
we will try to broadcast in cycle ten
and now the question is when do they
commit
remember that we can commit up to two
instructions per cycle so what's going
to happen is in cycle 10 we are going to
also try to commit the subtract we are
only committing this multiplication so
far we can commit two instructions we
will try to commit the next instruction
so in cycle 10 we will actually commit
this and now interestingly enough this
ad is done just in time to try to commit
it in cycle 11 so it's going to commit
in cycle 11.
so the final answer for the final part
of the quiz is that the commit is
happening in cycle 11 here